<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration, made and published by the King of France, vvhereby the princes, dukes, and barons therein named, are all proclaymed traytors, if within one moneth after the publication thereof, they doe not ceasse from armes, and personally present themselues vnto his Maiestie Published the 6. of August 1620. Stylo nouo. Faithfully translated according to the French copie.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1620-07-28. English</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844480</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844480</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06368)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1246:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration, made and published by the King of France, vvhereby the princes, dukes, and barons therein named, are all proclaymed traytors, if within one moneth after the publication thereof, they doe not ceasse from armes, and personally present themselues vnto his Maiestie Published the 6. of August 1620. Stylo nouo. Faithfully translated according to the French copie.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1620-07-28. English</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Beale?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Mertaigny the 28. of Iuly, anno 1620.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9297:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9297:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION, Made and publiſhed by the King of France, Whereby the Princes, Dukes, and Barons therein named, are all proclaymed Traytors, if within one moneth after <hi>the publication thereof, they doe not ceaſſe</hi> from Armes, and perſonally preſent themſelues vnto his MAIESTIE.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed the 6. of Auguſt 1620. <hi>Stylo Nouo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated according to the French Copie.</p>
            <p>1620.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9297:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9297:2"/>
            <head>A declaration made and publiſhed by the King of France, whereby the Princes, Dukes, and Barons therein named, are all proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Traytors, if within one moneth after the publication thereof they doe not ceaſſe from armes, and perſonally preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto his Maieſtie. Publiſhed the 6. of Auguſt, 1620. <hi>Stylo nouo.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>LEWES, By the grace of God, King of France and Nauarre, To all men to whom theſe preſents ſhall come, greeting. If ſince the time that We were inveſted with, and haue vnder-taken the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this State, We had failed in any thing, either in regard of the Queene Our moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lady and Mother, or in reſpect of the Princes &amp; noble Perſonages of Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, We would with more patience receiue and beare the troubles which therein at this preſent are ſtirred vp and rayſed againſt Vs. But calling to mind ſuch accidents as are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly paſt, and conſidering what fruit the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, graces, and benefits, by Vs ſo liberally imparted vnto thoſe, who at this day trouble Vs: Wee cannot ſo ſoone bewaile Our hard
<pb facs="tcp:9297:3"/>
fortune, as alſo that of all France in generall, but Wee muſt withall accuſe and vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the ſmall conſideration of thoſe, that reward Vs euill for good. For all men know, that preſently vpon Our acceptation and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the adminiſtration of publike af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, Our firſt care was to deliuer the Princes and great Perſons of Our Realme from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and trouble wherein they were, and to ſpeake truth, from vtter ruine and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which then was like to fall vpon them; and drew them neare vnto Our perſon: and nothing but the emulation and iealouſies that was then betweene them, hindred them from being of Our Councell, and priuie to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction and ordering of Our Princely affaires. Touching the Queene our moſt Princely Lady and Mother, Wee gaue and yeelded vnto her all that honor which the ſtate of things at that time might beare, and procured the meanes to make her enioy all contentments that ſhee could wiſh or deſire. After that when ſhe had withdrawne her ſelfe from Blois to Angou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſme, there to frame a publike complaint, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as ſhee ſaid) ſhee was hindred from the enioying of Our preſence, although for Our owne parts Wee were much offended at the behauiours of thoſe that were her aſſiſtants, and had power ſufficient to puniſh their inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, We were content for her ſatisfaction
<pb facs="tcp:9297:3"/>
to grant her all whatſoeuer ſhee deſired, the Townes, Forts, and gouernments which ſhee would chooſe, ſuch mony as ſhee required to haue; and not onely were pleaſed, that ſhee ſhould reſide neare vnto Vs, but did ſo inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeke it of her, that then at that time ſhee came to Vs to Tours, with ſuch and ſo great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence, that We were wholly out of doubt that nothing in ſubſequent time would alter her minde. Wee likewiſe, for her ſake, pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thoſe that had ayded and aſſiſted her, and made diuers of them Captaines of Our guard, which before had abandoned Vs to follow her. After We had effected all that, which We had promiſed vnto her, with long patience Wee expected, but could not ſee thoſe of her part performe that whereunto they were bound: and yet for all that, Wee abſtayned not from gratifying her in all things that ſhee deſired and required at Our hands, not only in reſpect of her ſelfe, but alſo of thoſe that held with her; as alſo continually to cauſe diuers great Perſonages and men of qualitie to viſite her, and inſtantly ſolicited her to come neare vnto Vs, ſo farre, that being aduertiſed that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne malicious ſpirits, made her beleeue, that Our deſire therein was cleane contrary to the outward ſhew We made: to giue her more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance both of Our intent &amp; the reſpect that We beare vnto her, We ſet forward to meete
<pb facs="tcp:9297:4"/>
her in the middle way, at ſuch time as ſhe had promiſed to come; and are perſwaded, that if therein ſhee had only beene ruled by her ſelfe, and her owne good diſpoſition, Wee ſhould not haue fayled at this preſent of a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and our Realme of an entire and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured tranquilitie. But vnmeaſurable ambition which prouoketh the ſpirits of many great Perſonages in Our Realme, that fill their heads with diſcontentments, and makes them weary of eaſe and quietneſſe, hath beene the cauſe that diſagreeing among themſelues, touching their owne particular affaires, they haue in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral plotted together to effect ſome nouelties in the State: and to trouble Our Realme, vpon and vnder the ſame pretences, which all thoſe that formerly attempted the ſame haue practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And becauſe they were perſwaded that the perſon of Our ſaid Lady and Mother in her reſpect, might better cloake, diſguiſe, and ſtrengthen theſe diſſeings; there is no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of artificiall practiſes wherewith they haue not ſerued their turnes, to put diſtruſt into her breaſt, to alter her good intentions, and to perſwade her that ſhee had wrong done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, if ſhee had not an abſolute authoritie giuen her in Our Realme. And although the euill (which therein maketh Vs too much feele her ouer-great facilitie) toucheth Vs to the quicke, yet Wee hold her excuſeable, being
<pb facs="tcp:9297:4"/>
perſwaded, that not many ſpirits in the world are able to withſtand and reſiſt ſo many, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, and damnable inuentions. And although We heare her name vſed in all places, and her ſignature and ſeale euen throughout all Our Prouinces, to authorize that which is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt Vs, yet We cannot be perſwaded but that her heart is wholly alienated from the ſame, and her ſoule altogether innocent. But for that, at the purſuit of the complaints that are made in her name throughout all Our Realme, and of the proteſtations to reforme Our State, Wee haue ſeene Our Couſin the Duke of Mayen withdraw himſelfe from Our Court, without taking leaue of Vs; the Duke de Vandoſme Our naturall brother follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, Our Couſin the Duke de Longueville being ſent for to come vnto Vs, refuſeth to do it; Our Couſin the Duke de Nemours gone from Vs in the night-time. And ſince that (which moſt grieueth Vs) Our deare and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Couſin the Earle of Soiſſons, and Our Couſin his mother, likewiſe gone from Our Court by night, then when We were vpon the point to honour him with the mariage of Our ſiſter: Which alſo was ſeconded by Our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall brother the great Prior of France; and ſoone after were aduertiſed that all of them were gone to Our ſaid Lady and Mother, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Dukes de Rets, de la Trimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,
<pb facs="tcp:9297:5"/>
de Rohan, and de Rohanois, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of the ſaid Dukes de Mayen and Eſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, to take order to leuy armes, &amp; to giue a beginning to the execution of their deſeignes: We vnderſtood, that as ſoone as they had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all Our Regiments, to put them into Metz, they intended therewith to diſarme all the inhabitants thereof. Wee were preſently informed of negotiations made with ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to cauſe them to enter into Our Realme, that the greateſt part of the Nobilitie of Our Prouinces are practiſed withall, the ſouldiers ſeduced, prouiſions of armes and munitions made, deſeignes agreed vpon to bee put in practiſe againſt certayne Townes, and Forts, Our money taken and ſtayed in the Receits of Xainctes, Saint Iohn, Fontenay, Angiers, Chinon, and other places: Commiſſions deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out (whereof ſome fell into Our hands) to leuy foote and horſe-men, garriſons put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Our Townes, Craon beſieged and taken. And that which touched Vs neareſt of all, was, to vnderſtand that Our Duchy of Normandie was like wholly to be loſt, whereby Wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that Our good Citie of Paris would by that meanes be brought to a miſerable and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull eſtate. Preferring the good of Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects before Our owne life, onely taking Our Guard with Vs, We went preſently to Roane, from whence the Duke de Longueville (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſhed
<pb facs="tcp:9297:5"/>
at Our reſolution) withdrew himſelfe, and gaue Vs meanes to aſſure that towne from the ſpoile, which without doubt, it had endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if Wee had not come thither; as it was publikely declared vnto Vs by Our Court of Parliament in the ſame Towne, at ſuch time as We there ſate in the ſeate of Iuſtice. After that, hauing within two dayes reaſſured the ſtate of that Towne, and ſeiſed vpon the old Palace, We went to Caen, where We entred into the Caſtle, &amp; made trenches cloſe to the walls, in ſuch manner that thoſe that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged within it, perceiued themſelues to bee out of all hope of any ayde, and yet ceaſed not inſolently to ſhoot at Vs, at ſuch time as they knew that We were gone to viſit the trenches: which neuertheleſſe, withdrew Vs not from v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing mercy and clemency towards them, and ſo much the rather, becauſe they made their excuſes, that they were commanded by Our ſaid Lady Mother, to hold the place ſtrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Vs: alwayes deſiring more and more to witneſſe and ſhew Our patience, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that Wee had vnto her. Since that Wee reduced the Townes of Alençon, Vernevil, Dreux, and la Ferte-Bernard, vnder Our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And now, for that Wee vnderſtand that the Armie that is in the field, vnder the borrowed name of Our ſaid Lady Mother, hath beſieged and taken the Towne of la Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſche,
<pb facs="tcp:9297:6"/>
wherein the hart of Our late moſt Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord and Father is buried, and marcheth forward to beſiege the Towne of Mans, Wee draw Our Armie thither to deliuer it from the ſiege which it feareth, and to withdraw the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the hands of inſolent ſouldiers, who hauing violated the fidelity which they owe vnto Vs, may well violate the reſpect which they owe to the memory, and to the aſhes of Our ſaid Lord and Father. But before Wee march forward, to employ Our iuſt and neceſſary armes, to ſuppreſſe the audaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thoſe that haue taken and beare armes againſt Vs, intruding vpon Our authority, and ſeeke to inuade Our Prouinces: Our deſire is, that euery man ſhould manifeſtly know and vnderſtand Our intent, and make thoſe that offend Vs, ſee that the greatnes of their faults (although moſt extreme) cannot attayne to the height of Our clemency, if they would haue recourſe thereunto; and that neglecting the ſame, We will and pretend to make them ſuffer and feele the rigour which the Lawes and Ordinances of Our Realme haue decreed againſt them. Therefore, We make it knowne that after We had taken order about theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, by the aduice of Our Councell, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Our moſt deare and onely louing bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Duke of Aniou, Our moſt deare and beloued Couſin the Prince of Conde, firſt
<pb facs="tcp:9297:6"/>
Prince of Our bloud, together with diuers Cardinalls, Dukes, Peeres, Officers of Our Crowne, and principall Lords of Our ſaid Councell; by their aduice, We haue decreed and ſignified, and by theſe preſents decree and ſignifie, that touching the Queene Our ſaid Lady and Mother, We doe not beleeue, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can be perſwaded, that ſhee hath forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the amity and loue which nature bindeth her to beare vnto Vs, and the memorie of Our ſaid Lord and Father exacteth from her: and which Wee haue ſought to deſerue at her hands. And although it ſhould fall out, that ſhee ſhould vſe other comportments towards Vs then ſhee ought to doe, We are determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with religious patience to endure them, and that when Our Army approcheth neare vnto that which is aſſembled in her name, We will not employ Our forces to any other end, then to deliuer her out of the hands of thoſe, who to the preiudice of Vs and our Realme, captiuate her ſpirits, and her will; and to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the effecting of thoſe deſſeignes which they haue for the ruine of Our ſtate. Touching Our Couſin the Earle of Soiſſons, and Our Couſin the Counteſſe his Mother, the Dukes de Vandoſme, the great Prior of France, the Dukes de Longueville, de Nemours, de May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, d'Eſpernon, de Rets, de la Trimoville, de Rohan, de Rohanois, the Marſhall de Bois
<pb facs="tcp:9297:7"/>
Dauphin, the Earle de Candale, the Marquis de la Valette, the Archbiſhop of Tholoſe, and others the Officers of Our Crowne, We en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne and moſt expreſly command them, to leaue off their Armes, and to ſurceaſe from all acts of hoſtilitie againſt Our ſubiects; to leaue all leagues and confederacies, as well within as without Our Realmes, and within one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth next after enſuing the Publication of theſe preſents, to come perſonally vnto Vs, thereby to giue vs more and better aſſurance: which doing, We will remit all crimes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences by them done vnto Vs, in this laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, promiſing to receiue them againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Our fauour, and giue ſuch aſſurance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by writing, as they ſhall thinke neceſſary for the ſame: likewiſe commanding all others that haue taken their parts, and vnder the name of Our ſaid Lady and Mother haue borne armes, and conſequently, vſed acts of hoſtility, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that haue made themſelues culpable towards Vs, that if they withdraw themſelues from the ſaid armes, and before the neareſt Iudges that ſhall be vnto them, declare, that they willingly withdraw themſelues from the ſaid party, league, and aſſociation, they ſhall be acquitted and diſcharged by vertue of theſe preſents, and neuer be troubled nor moleſted for the ſame: and fayling to doe it, &amp; to accept of this Our preſent pardon, within the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:9297:7"/>
time, which being once paſt, for the preſent as well as then, We haue and by theſe preſents doe declare al the ſaid Princes, Dukes, Peeres, and Officers of Our Crowne aforeſaid, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of what quality, ſtate, and condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be, which haue directly or indirectly beene participants in the ſaid aſſociations, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, practiſes, leuies, bearing of armes, &amp; acts aforeſaid, mentioned, to be guiltie of high treaſon, &amp; perturbers of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peace and quietneſſe of Our Realme, and thereby to haue incurred the forfeiture of all honors, gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, dignities, offices, benefices, ſeiſes, lands, and Signiouries whatſoeuer they hold of Vs, to be revnited to Our Crowne. And for the better declaration and execution of the paynes impoſed vpon, and ſet downe againſt ſuch crimes, by the Lawes and Ordinances of Our Realme, We will that all Our Iudges ſhal proceed orderly againſt them and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, in euery place, where the knowledge thereof is brought vnto them. And therefore command Our louing and faithfull Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of Our Courts of Parliament, Bailifes, Stewards, Iudges, or their Lieutenants, and all others Our Iuſtices and Officers, to whom particularly it ſhall or may appertayne, to cauſe theſe Our preſent Letters of Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be read, publiſhed, and regiſtred, and from point to point exactly to execute, keepe,
<pb facs="tcp:9297:8"/>
and inuiolably obſerue the ſame, according to the tenour and forme thereof, charging Our Attourneyes generall and their Subſtitutes, to make all purſuites, and to vſe all diligence therein according to the tenour of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for ſuch is Our pleaſure: In witneſſe whereof, We haue cauſed Our Seale to be ſet to theſe preſents. Giuen at Mertaigny the 28. of Iuly, Anno 1620. and of Our reigne the 11.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed <hi>Lewes.</hi>
               </signed>
               <signed>And ſomewhat lower, By the King, Subſcribed, <hi>De Lomenie.</hi>
               </signed>
Sealed with the great Seale in yellow waxe, with two Labels.
</closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Read, publiſhed, regiſtred and heard at the requeſt of the Kings Attourney generall: and order taken that Copies ſhould be ſent to all Balifwicks and Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, there to be read, publiſhed, regiſtred, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted according to their forme and tenor, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curements of the Subſtitutes of the ſaid Attourney ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and with commiſſion to enioyne them to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the ſame within the moneth. At Paris in the Court of Parliament, the 6. of Auguſt. 1620.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed <hi>Voiſin.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <pb facs="tcp:9297:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
